Guide to the Kirby Petroleum Company / George Sawtelle Executive records, 1921-1967, bulk 1931-1953 MS 504
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Kirby Petroleum Company / George Sawtelle Executive Records
1921-1967, bulk 1931-1953
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Kirby Petroleum Company
MS 504
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
The materials in this collection are from the Houston-based Kirby Petroleum Company and the records of George Sawtelle, president and later chairman of the company to 1965. This collection consists of 2.5 linear feet of photographs, correspondence, business records, clippings, and technical papers. The primary correspondents are John H. Kirby, Clint Murchison, Cooper Ragan, and George Sawtelle. This material provides a valuable look at the early days of the oil industry in Texas. In particular, this collection documents through correspondence the concerns and business goals of oil men from the 1920s through the 1940s.
Historical Note
The Kirby Petroleum Company/George Sawtelle records offers a glimpse into the early 20th century oil boom in Texas primarily through the correspondence of George Sawtelle, who served as president of the company for more than 20 years. Sawtelle died September 4, 1967.
The origin of the Kirby Petroleum Company can be traced back to 1921 when John Henry Kirby, a pioneer in the development of the Houston business community, formed Kirby Petroleum Company, an oil and gas exploration and development company. Kirby Petroleum Company operated as a Houston-based independent oil and gas exploration and development company until 1956 when, after the sale of its producing properties, the remaining non-producing acreage was merged with three other independent oil and gas companies to form Kirby VenSyn Petroleum Company, a publicly traded company. As a result of the mergers, the Murchison family of Dallas, later noted for its ownership of the Dallas Cowboys, owned approximately 35 percent of Kirby. Kirby VenSyn Petroleum Company changed its name to Kirby Petroleum Co. in 1957 and adopted the name Kirby Industries, Inc. in 1967. As of 2005, the company, still based in Houston, is known as Kirby Corp. although its primary business is transporting bulk liquid products on the Mississippi River System and Gulf Intracoastal Waterway. Kirby Corporation. (2001). Company History. Retrieved March 23, 2005 from http://www.kmtc.com/corp/history.cfm
George Sawtelle was born in Wheeling Virginia on February 27, 1892. He graduated in 1916 from Lehigh University with a bachelor of science degree in chemistry. In 1916, he was in the U.S. Army and stationed on the border with Mexico. During World War I, he served in France in the Seventh Field Artillery Brigade and rose to the rank of captain. His brigade commander thought highly enough of the young captain to write Sawtelle a letter stating that he had been recommended for promotion to major. That letter is located in box 5, folder 4. From 1920 to 1921, Sawtelle, a longtime football enthusiast, served as an assistant football coach at Northwestern University. He joined Kirby Petroleum Company in 1922. In 1924, he was the general manager and chief geologist of the company. Eventually, he rose to the presidency of the company, a position he held for more than 20 years. He resigned as chairman of the Kirby board in 1965. As the result of a heart attack, he died Sunday, September 3, 1967 in Austin, Texas.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 2.5 linear feet of photographs, correspondence, business records, clippings, and technical papers. The materials are from the Houston-based Kirby Petroleum Company and the records of George Sawtelle, who was president of the company for more than 20 years. The inclusive dates for the materials are 1921-1967, although the bulk of the materials cover the years 1931-1953. The primary correspondents are John H. Kirby, Clint Murchison, Cooper Ragan, and George Sawtelle. This material provides a valuable look at the early days of the oil industry in Texas. In particular it documents through correspondence the concerns and business goals of oil men from the 1920s through the 1940s. In addition, the personal correspondence of George Sawtelle reveals his close ties to family and business colleagues, as well has his charitable work. This collection does not contain significant amounts of published corporate materials, such as annual reports or press releases.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Accruals
No future additions are expected for this material.
Acquisition Information
Mary Alice Sawtelle of Houston, Texas, donated this material to the Woodson Research Center in February 2004.
Index Terms
Subjects
Oil fields -- Texas; Oil well drilling rigs; Petroleum industry and trade; Petroleum -- Texas; Business
Document Types
letters (correspondence); compact discs; business records; digital images; memorandums; technical reports; clippings (information artifacts); personal correspondence; telegrams; photographs; black-and-white photographs; corrrespondence
Places
Texas, East; Texas, West; Houston (Tex.) -- History.; Houston (Tex.) -- Business, industries, and trades -- Petroleum; Texas -- History, Local.; Houston (Tex.) -- Business, industries, and trades -- Oil field equipment.
Subjects (Persons)
Sawtelle, George; Murchison, Clinton Williams Sr.; Pratt, Wallace; Ragan, Cooper Kirby; Kirby, John H.; Christian, W. G.
Subjects (Corporations)
Kirby Petroleum Company
- Series I: Alphabetical files A-L, 33789
  - A-B: Business and Personal Correspondence from or to George Sawtelle, 1946-1967; 33809 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - C: Business and Personal Correspondence between George Sawtelle and C.E. Cook and others, 1937-1967; 33808 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence of Christian, W.G., 1922-1923; 33807 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - D: Correspondence to or from George Sawtelle, 1928-1966; 33806 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence of Davis, Morgan, 1945-1966; 33805 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - E: correspondence, 1929-1967; 33804 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Estimates on Refinery,", 1922; 33803 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - F: Correspondence to G. Sawtelle, 1948-1955; 33802 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - G: Correspondence, 1929-1956; 33801 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Guideline for Applying Protective Coatings to Underground Pipelines, 1929; 33800 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - H: Correspondence, 1938-1965; 33799 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Houston Geological Society, 1929-1959; 33798 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - I-J: Correspondence, 1928-1967; 33797 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - K: Correspondence related to leases and Kirby Oil, 1928-1953; 33796 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kirby, John H., 1922-1930; 33795 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Kirby Petroleum Company: corporate history, clippings, 2001-2002; 33794 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kirby [Petroleum Co.] correspondence, memos; folder 1 of 2, 1921-1946; 33793 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kirby [Petroleum Co.] correspondence, memos; folder 2 of 2, 1921-1946; 33792 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - L: Correspondence, 1940-1966; 33791 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Lehigh University, 1948-1964; 33790 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series II: Alphabetical files M-Z, 33754
  - M: Correspondence, 1929-1954; 33788 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Mattinson, J.A., 1932-1937; 33787 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mays, Gene, 1929-1936; 33786 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mid-Continent Oil & Gas Assoc., 1941-1943; 33785 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Mincon, map, correspondence, DMEA project on Elk Ridge properties, Colorado, 1956; 33784 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Minister, H., 1932-1934; 33783 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Moncrief, W.A., 1928-1940; 33782 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Muldoon Well, 1941-1942; 33781 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Murchison, Clint; dissolution of Kirby [Petroleum Co.], 1940-1955; 33780 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - N: Correspondence, 1930-1962; 33779 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Neath, J.A., 1939-1957; 33778 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with F.C. O'Keefe, Oahu Railway and Land Company, and Oliphant and Co., 1951-1959; 33777 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Opinions on Oil Leases, 1930-1937; 33776 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Pratts, Wallace, 1938-1960; 33775 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - P: Correspondence, 1944-1960; 33774 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - R: Correspondence, 1944-1967; 33773 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Ragan, Cooper, 1932-1937; 33772 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Ragan, Cooper, 1938-1955; 33771 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Reiter, Bosey, 1937-1940; 33770 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - S: Correspondence, 1929-1967; 33769 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - St. Thomas High School - George Strake, 1939; 33768 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Sawtelle, George, 1923-1959; 33767 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sawtelle, George, 1960-1966; 33766 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sawtelle, George,: clippings, obituaries, memorials, birth certificate, military record, 1918-1967; 33765 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sawtelle Family, 1940-1944; 33764 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sawtelle Family, 1954-1965; 33763 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Stroube, H.R. & W.C., 1933-1936; 33762 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Suman, John R., 1939-1953; 33761 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - T: Correspondence, 1942-1963; 33760 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Texas Oil & Gas Conservation Assoc., 1931-1933; 33759 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - V, W: Correspondence, 1951-1965; 33758 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Y, Z: Correspondence, 1925-1962; 33757 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Yates Field, 1935-1945; 33756 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Photographs (printed scans and CD), 33755 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    General note
    Photos include an original portrait of George Sawtelle, ca. 1960s, and an original image of a man standing on a stack of pipe, ca. 1930s. The other images are prints of scans from original images, which also are contained on the CD as high resolution tif files. The scanned images include subjects such as oil gushers, derricks and roughnecks from the 1920s and 1930s.